Chris Anderson: The rights of citizens,
كريس أندرسون: حقوق المواطنين
the future of the Internet.
مستقبل الإنترنت
So I would like to welcome to the TED stage
إذن أريد أن أرحب على مسرح TED
the man behind those revelations,
بالرجل وراء هذه الإكتشافات
Ed Snowden.
إد سنودن.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Ed is in a remote location somewhere in Russia
إد موجود في مكان بعيد في روسيا
controlling this bot from his laptop,
يتحكم بهذا الروبوت من خلال لابتوبه
so he can see what the bot can see.
حتى يرى ما بإمكان الروبوت أن يرى,
Ed, welcome to the TED stage.
إد مرحبًا بك على مسرح TED
What can you see, as a matter of fact?
ماذا بإمكانك أن ترى في الحقيقة؟
Edward Snowden: Ha, I can see everyone.
إدوارد سنودن: ها بإمكاني أن أرى كل شخص.
This is amazing.
هذا مذهل!
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
CA: Ed, some questions for you.
كريس: إد بعض الأسئلة لك.
You've been called many things
تم نعتك بالعديد من الصفات
in the last few months.
خلال الشهور القليلة الماضية;
You've been called a whistleblower, a traitor,
تم نعتك بكاشف الفساد خائن
a hero.
بطل
What words would you describe yourself with?
ماهي الصفات التي تود أن تصف نفسك بها؟
ES: You know, everybody who is involved
إد: أنت تعرف كل شخص تعرض
with this debate
لهذا النقاش
has been struggling over me and my personality
يعاني ليتفهمني وليتفهم شخصيتي
and how to describe me.
وكيف بإمكانه أن يصفني.
But when I think about it,
لكن عندما أفكر في الأمر;
this isn't the question that we should be struggling with.
لا يتوجب علينا أن نضيع وقتنا في هذا السؤال
Who I am really doesn't matter at all.
من أنا حقيقة لا يهم كثيرًا.
If I'm the worst person in the world,
إذا كنتُ اسوأ شخص في العالم
you can hate me and move on.
بإمكانك أن تكرهني وتمضي قدمًا
What really matters here are the issues.
ما يهم هاهنا حقيقتاً هذه القضايا.
What really matters here is the kind of government we want,
ما يهم في الواقع هنا نوع الحكومة التي نريدها,
the kind of Internet we want,
نوع الإنترنت الذي نريده,
the kind of relationship between people
نوع العلاقات بين الناس
and societies.
والمجتمعات.
And that's what I'm hoping the debate will move towards,
وهذا ما آمل أن يتجه إليه هذا النقاش,
and we've seen that increasing over time.
ونحنا شاهدنا تقدمًا ملحوظًا خلال الزمن.
If I had to describe myself,
إذا توجب علي أن اصف نفسي
I wouldn't use words like "hero."
لن استخدم كلمة مثل " بطل"
I wouldn't use "patriot," and I wouldn't use "traitor."
ولن استخدم كلمة مثل "وطني" و لن استخدم كلمة مثل " خائن".
I'd say I'm an American and I'm a citizen,
سوف أقول أنني مواطن أمريكي
just like everyone else.
تمامًا كأي شخص آخر.
CA: So just to give some context
كريس: إذن كي أعطي بعض الخلفية
for those who don't know the whole story --
لأولئك الذين لايعرفون القصة كاملة--
(Applause) —
(تصفيق)--
this time a year ago, you were stationed in Hawaii
مثل هذا الوقت من السنة الماضية كنت مقيمًا في هاواي
working as a consultant to the NSA.
تعمل كمستشار لNSA
As a sysadmin, you had access
كمسؤول نظامي أتيح لك الدخول
to their systems,
إلى أنظمتهم
and you began revealing certain classified documents
و أنت بدأت بكشف بعض الملفات المصنفة
to some handpicked journalists
لبعض الصحفين المختارين
leading the way to June's revelations.
والتي أدت إلى كشوفات حزيران.
Now, what propelled you to do this?
الآن ماالذي دفعك للقيام بذلك؟
ES: You know,
إد: أنت تعرف
when I was sitting in Hawaii,
عندما كنت مقيمًا في هاواي
and the years before, when I was working in the intelligence community,
وخلال السنين الماضية عندما عملت مع جهاز الإستخبارات
I saw a lot of things that had disturbed me.
رأيت العديد من الأشياء التي أزعجتني
We do a lot of good things in the intelligence community,
نحن نقوم بالعديد من الأشياء الجيدة في جهاز الإستخبارات
things that need to be done,
أشياء مهمة
and things that help everyone.
و أشياء تخدم الجميع.
But there are also things that go too far.
لكن هنالك أشياء أيضًا تتخطى ذلك.
There are things that shouldn't be done,
هنالك أشياء لايتوجب القيام بها
and decisions that were being made in secret
وقرارات تُصنع في السر
without the public's awareness,
بعيدًا عن وعي العامة
without the public's consent,
ومن غير موافقتهم,
and without even our representatives in government
ومن غير حتى معرفة ممثلينا في الحكومة
having knowledge of these programs.
بوجود هذه البرامج.
When I really came to struggle with these issues,
عندما بدأت مكافحة هذه البرامج
I thought to myself,
فكرت
how can I do this in the most responsible way,
كيف بإمكاني أن أقوم بهذا العمل بالطريقة الأكثر مسؤلية
that maximizes the public benefit
والتي تزيد من المصلحة العامة
while minimizing the risks?
بينما تقلل الخطر؟
And out of all the solutions that I could come up with,
و من بين كل الحلول التي توصلت لها
out of going to Congress,
من خلال زيارة الكونغرس
when there were no laws,
عندما لم يكن هنالك قوانين
there were no legal protections
بإمكانها أن تحمي
for a private employee,
الموظف الخاص
a contractor in intelligence like myself,
المتعاقد في الإستخبارات مثلي
there was a risk that I would be buried along with the information
كان هنالك خطورة أن يتم دفني مع هذه المعلومات
and the public would never find out.
وأن العامة لن يعرفوا أي شيء.
But the First Amendment of the United States Constitution
لكن التعديل الدستوري الأمريكي الأول
guarantees us a free press for a reason,
ضمن لنا حرية الصحافة لسبب
and that's to enable an adversarial press,
وهو أن أسمح للصحافة المعادية
to challenge the government,
بتحدي الحكومة
but also to work together with the government,
لكن أيضًا كي تعمل سوياً مع الحكومة
to have a dialogue and debate about how we can
لتتبنى النقاش والجدال حول كيفية
inform the public about matters of vital importance
إعلام العامة عن الأمور ذات الأهمية القصوة,
without putting our national security at risk.
من غير تعريض أمننا القومي للخطر.
And by working with journalists,
ومن خلال العمل مع الصحفين
by giving all of my information
وإعطاء كل المعلومات
back to the American people,
التي املكها للشعب الأمريكي
rather than trusting myself to make
عوضًا عن أن أفوض نفسي
the decisions about publication,
لإتخاذ قرار النشر
we've had a robust debate
توصلنا لنقاشات قوية
with a deep investment by the government
إستثمرت فيها الحكومة بعمق
that I think has resulted in a benefit for everyone.
والتي أعتقد أنها أوجدت مصلحة عامة للجميع.
And the risks that have been threatened,
أيضًا المخاطر التي تهددتنا
the risks that have been played up
والتي تم التلاعب بها
by the government
من قبل الحكومة
have never materialized.
لم يتم تجسيدها.
We've never seen any evidence
نحن لم نرى أية أدلة
of even a single instance of specific harm,
أو حتى حادثة مجردة لأذى معين
and because of that,
وبسبب ذلك
I'm comfortable with the decisions that I made.
أنا مرتاح مع القرار الذي قمت به
CA: So let me show the audience
كريس: إذن دعني أشارك الحضور
a couple of examples of what you revealed.
بعض الأمثلة عن الأشياء التي كشفتها.
If we could have a slide up, and Ed,
هل بإمكاننا رفع شريحة العرض و إد
I don't know whether you can see,
لا أعرف إذا كان بإمكانك أن ترى
the slides are here.
هاهي الشريحة.
This is a slide of the PRISM program,
هذه شريحة لبرنامج PRISM
and maybe you could tell the audience
ولربما كان بإمكانك أن تُخبر الحضور
what that was that was revealed.
مالشيء الذي تم الكشف عنه.
ES: The best way to understand PRISM,
إد: أفضل طريقة لفهم PRISM
because there's been a little bit of controversy,
لأنه كان هنالك بعض الجدل
is to first talk about what PRISM isn't.
علي أولاً أن أتحدث عن الأشياء التي لاتمثلها PRISM
Much of the debate in the U.S. has been about metadata.
الكثير من الجدل في الولايات المتحدة كان عن البيانات الوصفية.
They've said it's just metadata, it's just metadata,
قالوا أنها فقط بيانات وصفية
and they're talking about a specific legal authority
وهم يتحدثون عن سلطة قانونية
called Section 215 of the Patriot Act.
تسمى المقطع215 من قانون الباتريوت.
That allows sort of a warrantless wiretapping,
والذي يمنح إذنًا قضائيًا للتصنت على المحادثات الهاتفية
mass surveillance of the entire country's
من خلال مراقبة شاملة للسجلات الهاتفية
phone records, things like that --
في الدولة, أشياء مثل --
who you're talking to,
إلى من تتحدث
when you're talking to them,
متى تتحدث إليهم
where you traveled.
أين سافرت.
These are all metadata events.
كل هذه أحداث لبيانات وصفية.
PRISM is about content.
الـ PRISM هو عن المحتوى.
It's a program through which the government could
هو برنامج من خلاله يمكن للحكومة
compel corporate America,
أن تجبر شركة كوابرات أمريكا
it could deputize corporate America
و تفوضها
to do its dirty work for the NSA.
لكي تقوم بعملها القذر لالـ NSA.
And even though some of these companies did resist,
وبالرغم من أن معظم هذه الشركات قاومت,
even though some of them --
حتى أن بعضها
I believe Yahoo was one of them —
أعتقد ياهو كانت إحداها
challenged them in court, they all lost,
تحدتهم في المحكمة لكنها خسرت
because it was never tried by an open court.
لأنها لم تجرب محكمة مفتوحة.
They were only tried by a secret court.
هم جربوا فقط محكمة سرية.
And something that we've seen,
أحد الأشياء التي رأيناها
something about the PRISM program that's very concerning to me is,
تتعلق ببرنامج ال PRISM والذي يثير قلقي
there's been a talking point in the U.S. government
كانت هنالك نقطة نقاش في حكومة الولايات
where they've said 15 federal judges
حيث قالوا أن 15 قاضيًا فيدراليًا
have reviewed these programs and found them to be lawful,
قاموا بمراجعة هذه البرامج ووجدوها قانونية
but what they don't tell you
لكن مالايخبرونك هو
is those are secret judges
أن هؤلاء القضاء كانوا سريين
in a secret court
في محكمة سرية
based on secret interpretations of law
إعتمادًا على تأويلات سرية للقانون
that's considered 34,000 warrant requests
والتي إعتبرت 34000 مذكرة
over 33 years,
خلال 33 سنة
and in 33 years only rejected
وخلال هذه ال33 سنة تم رفض
11 government requests.
11 طلب حكومي.
These aren't the people that we want deciding
هؤلاء ليسوا الأشخاص الذين نريدهم كي يقرروا عنا
what the role of corporate America
ما دور كوابرت امريكا
in a free and open Internet should be.
في مايتوجب على الإنترنت كي يصبح حرًا ومجانيًا؟
CA: Now, this slide that we're showing here
كريس: الآن هذه الشريحة التي نعرضها هنا
shows the dates in which
ترينا التواريخ التي
different technology companies, Internet companies,
أنضمت خلالها الشركات التقنية وشركات الإنترنت
are alleged to have joined the program,
إلى البرنامج
and where data collection began from them.
وأين إبتدأ جمع البيانات منهم.
Now, they have denied collaborating with the NSA.
الآن هم أنكروا التعاون مع الNSA
How was that data collected by the NSA?
كيف تم جمع هذه البيانات بواسطة الNSA؟
ES: Right. So the NSA's own slides
إد: صحيح! إذن شرائح الNSA
refer to it as direct access.
تشير إليها كمصدر مباشر
What that means to an actual NSA analyst,
ماذا يعني هذا لخبير تحليلي في الNSA
someone like me who was working as an intelligence analyst
شخص مثلي كان يعمل كخبير تحليلي للإستخبارات
targeting, Chinese cyber-hackers,
يستهدف الهاكرز الصينين
things like that, in Hawaii,
أشياء مثل هذه في هاواي
is the provenance of that data
هي مصدر البيانات
is directly from their servers.
مباشرة من السيرفر.
It doesn't mean
هذا لايعني
that there's a group of company representatives
أن هنالك مجموعة من ممثلي الشركة
sitting in a smoky room with the NSA
يجلسون في غرفة مليئة بالدخان مع الNSA
palling around and making back-room deals
يتصادقون ويعقدون صفقات جانبية
about how they're going to give this stuff away.
عن طريقة تبادل المعلومات.
Now each company handles it different ways.
الآن كل شركة تعالج الأمر بطرق مختلفة
Some are responsible.
البعض مسؤول
Some are somewhat less responsible.
والبعض الأخر أقل مسؤولية
But the bottom line is, when we talk about
لكن الخلاصة أننا عندما نتحدث
how this information is given,
عن ماهية إعطاء هذه المعلومات
it's coming from the companies themselves.
هي تأتي من الشركات نفسها.
It's not stolen from the lines.
لا يتم سرقتها من الخطوط.
But there's an important thing to remember here:
لكن هنالك شيء يجب تذكره هنا
even though companies pushed back,
بالرغم من أن هذه الشركات تهربت
even though companies demanded,
لكنها مازالت مطلوبة
hey, let's do this through a warrant process,
دعونا نقوم بذلك من خلال عملية مجازة قانونيًا
let's do this
دعونا نقوم بهذا
where we actually have some sort of legal review,
حيث نملك مراجعة قانونية,
some sort of basis for handing over
كبعض القواعد لتقديم
these users' data,
معلومات المستخدمين هذه,
we saw stories in the Washington Post last year
رأينا بعض القصص على صفحات واشنطون بوست السنة الماضية
that weren't as well reported as the PRISM story
لم يتم الإخبار عنها كما تم الإخبار عن قصة ال PRISM
that said the NSA broke in
والتي أخبرت عن إختراق الNSA
to the data center communications
لمركز بيانات التواصل
between Google to itself
بين قوقل لنفسه.
and Yahoo to itself.
وياهو لنفسها.
So even these companies that are cooperating
إذن حتى هذه الشركات التي تساهم
in at least a compelled but hopefully lawful manner
على الأقل تساهم قسرًا لكن آمل بطريقة مشروعة
with the NSA,
مع الNSA.
the NSA isn't satisfied with that,
لكن الNSA لم تكن راضية.
and because of that, we need our companies
وبسبب ذلك نحن نحتاج شركاتنا
to work very hard
لتعمل كادحة
to guarantee that they're going to represent
لتضمن لنا أنها ستمثل
the interests of the user, and also advocate
مصالح المستخدم وأيضًا ستدافع
for the rights of the users.
عن حقوق المستخدمين
And I think over the last year,
أيضًا فكرت خلال السنة الماضية
we've seen the companies that are named
نحن شاهدنا الشركات التي تم ذكرها
on the PRISM slides
على شريحة الPRISM
take great strides to do that,
تتخذ خطوات عظيمة لتقوم بذلك
and I encourage them to continue.
وأنا أشجعهم على المواصلة.
CA: What more should they do?
كريس: ماذا يتوجب عليهم القيام به أكثر؟
ES: The biggest thing that an Internet company
إد: أكبر الأشياء التي بإمكان أي شركة إنترنت
in America can do today, right now,
في أمريكا أن تقوم به اليوم في هذه اللحظة
without consulting with lawyers,
من غير إستشارة محامين
to protect the rights of users worldwide,
حتى تحمي حقوق مستخدميها حول العالم
is to enable SSL web encryption
هو أن تسمح بإستخدام شفرة الSSL على الإنترنت
on every page you visit.
على كل صفحة تقوم بزيارتها.
The reason this matters is today,
السبب الذي لأجله يعتبر هذا مهمًا اليوم;
if you go to look at a copy of "1984" on Amazon.com,
هو إذا كان بمقدورك أن تنظر إلى نسخة من عام 1984 على موقع أمازون
the NSA can see a record of that,
بإمكان الNSA أن ترى تسجيل لذلك
the Russian intelligence service can see a record of that,
وبإمكان الإستخبارت الروسية أيضًا أن ترى نسخة
the Chinese service can see a record of that,
وكذلك الصينية
the French service, the German service,
والإستخبارات الفرنسية والإستخبارات الألمانية
the services of Andorra.
وإستخبارات اندورا.
They can all see it because it's unencrypted.
بإمكانهم جيمعًا أن يروا نسخة لأنها غيرمشفرة.
The world's library is Amazon.com,
موقع أمازون هو مكتبة العالم
but not only do they not support encryption by default,
لكن ليس فقط هم لايدعمون خدمات التشفير من خلال الخيار التلقائي
you cannot choose to use encryption
لكن لا يعطونك خيار إستخدامه
when browsing through books.
عند البحث خلال الكتب,
This is something that we need to change,
هذا شيء نحتاج تغيره.
not just for Amazon, I don't mean to single them out,
ليس فقط لأمازون لا أعني تميزهم عن البقية
but they're a great example.
لكنهم مثال جيد.
All companies need to move
كل الشركات تحتاج لأن تنتقل
to an encrypted browsing habit by default
إلى خدمات بحث مشفرة تلقائية
for all users who haven't taken any action
لكل المستخدمين الذين لم يتخذوا أية مبادرة
or picked any special methods on their own.
أو إختاروا أية طريقة خاصة من تلقاء أنفسهم.
That'll increase the privacy and the rights
سيعزز هذا الخصوصية والحقوق
that people enjoy worldwide.
التي يستمتع بها الناس في العالم.
CA: Ed, come with me to this part of the stage.
كريس: إد تعال معي إلى هذا الجزء من المنصة.
I want to show you the next slide here. (Applause)
أريد أن أريك الشريحة القادمة هاهنا (تصفيق)
This is a program called Boundless Informant.
هذا برنامج يسمى معلومات غير مقيدة.
What is that?
ماهذا؟
ES: So, I've got to give credit to the NSA
إد: إذن علي أن أمنح بعض التقدير لالـNSA
for using appropriate names on this.
لإستخدامها أسماً ملائمًا هاهنا.
This is one of my favorite NSA cryptonyms.
هذا أحد أفضل الأسماء الحركية لالـNSA.
Boundless Informant
معلومات غير مقيدة
is a program that the NSA hid from Congress.
هو برنامج اخفته الـNSA من الكونغرس.
The NSA was previously asked by Congress,
طُلب من الـNSA مُسبقًا عن طريق الكونغرس
was there any ability that they had
إذا كان لديها أي قدرة على إعطاء
to even give a rough ballpark estimate
تقدير تقريبي
of the amount of American communications
لكمية الإتصالات الأمريكية
that were being intercepted.
التي تم التعرض لها.
They said no. They said, we don't track those stats,
لكنهم رفضوا. قالوا أنهم لايتتبعون هذه الإحصائيات
and we can't track those stats.
و لايمكنهم ذلك.
We can't tell you how many communications
لانستطيع إخباركم عن عدد الإتصالات
we're intercepting around the world,
التي نخترقها حول العالم
because to tell you that would be
لأن إخباركم بذلك
to invade your privacy.
يعتبر تعدي على خصوصيتكم.
Now, I really appreciate that sentiment from them,
الآن حقيقة اقدر وجهة نظرهم
but the reality, when you look at this slide is,
لكن عندما تنظرون إلى شريحة العرض هذه
not only do they have the capability,
سترون هم ليس لديهم فقط المقدرة
the capability already exists.
المقدرة موجودة اصلاً.
It's already in place.
ويتم إستخدامها.
The NSA has its own internal data format
الNSA لها نظامها الخاص لتنسيق البيانات
that tracks both ends of a communication,
والذي يترصد طرفي الإتصال
and if it says,
و إذا أخبر
this communication came from America,
عن أن هذا الإتصال صادر من أمريكا
they can tell Congress how many of those communications
بإمكانهم إخبار الكونغرس عن عدد هذه الإتصالات
they have today, right now.
التي ترصدوها اليوم في هذه اللحظة
And what Boundless Informant tells us
و ماذا تخبرنا المعلومات غير المقيدة
is more communications are being intercepted
هو أن الكثير من الإتصالات التي يتم إختراقها
in America about Americans
في أمريكا تصدر من أمريكين
than there are in Russia about Russians.
وهي أكثر من تلك التي يتم اختراقها وتصدر في روسيا من خلال روس.
I'm not sure that's what an intelligence agency
أنا لست متأكد إذا كان هذا مايجب أن تصبو
should be aiming for.
إليه وكالة الإستخبارات.
CA: Ed, there was a story broken in the Washington Post,
كريس: كانت هنالك قصة تصدرت الواشنطون بوست
again from your data.
من المعلومات التي شاركتها.
The headline says,
العناوين الرئيسية تقول
"NSA broke privacy rules
ال NSA إخترقت قوانين الخصوصية
thousands of times per year."
آلاف المرات خلال السنة
Tell us about that.
حدثنا عن ذلك.
ES: We also heard in Congressional testimony last year,
إد: العام الماضي نحن أيضًا سمعنا شهادة في الكونغرس
it was an amazing thing for someone like me
كانت مذهلة لشخص مثلي
who came from the NSA
والذي كان جزء من الNSA
and who's seen the actual internal documents,
ورأى مستندات الإنترنت الحقيقية
knows what's in them,
ويعرف مابداخلها
to see officials testifying under oath
ليرى أشخاص يشهدون تحت القسم
that there had been no abuses,
أنه لاتوجد أية تعديات
that there had been no violations of the NSA's rules,
وأنه لم يكن هنالك أية تجاوزات لقوانين الNSA
when we knew this story was coming.
عندما عرفنا بصدور هذه القصة.
But what's especially interesting about this,
لكن أكثر الأشياء إثارة في هذا
about the fact that the NSA has violated
هي حقيقة أن الNSA تجاوزت
their own rules, their own laws
قوانينها وقواعدها
thousands of times in a single year,
آلاف المرات في سنة واحدة
including one event by itself,
تضمنت حادثة واحدة
one event out of those 2,776,
من 2776 حالة
that affected more than 3,000 people.
أثرت على أكثر من 3000 شخص.
In another event, they intercepted
في حادثة أخرى هم إخترقوا
all the calls in Washington, D.C., by accident.
كل المكالمات في واشنطون دي سي عن طريق الخطاء.
What's amazing about this,
المذهل في هذا الأمر
this report, that didn't get that much attention,
التقرير الذي لم يحوذ على الكثير من الإنتباه
is the fact that not only were there 2,776 abuses,
هو حقيقة أنه لم يكن هنالك 2776 إعتداء فقط
the chairman of the Senate Intelligence Committee,
لكن رئيسة لجنة الإستخبارات في مجلس الشيوخ
Dianne Feinstein, had not seen this report
ديان فينستين لم ترى هذا التقرير
until the Washington Post contacted her
حتى أتصلت بها صحيفة الواشنطون بوست
asking for comment on the report.
وطلبت منها التعليق على التقرير.
And she then requested a copy from the NSA
حينها طلبت نسخة من الNSA
and received it,
و تحصلت عليها
but had never seen this before that.
لكنها لم ترى ذلك التقرير قبل ذلك.
What does that say about the state of oversight
ماذا يخبرنا هذا عن حالة الرقابة
in American intelligence
في الإستخبارات الأمريكية
when the chairman of the Senate Intelligence Committee
عندما لا يكون لدى رئيسة الإستخبارات في مجلس الشيوخ
has no idea that the rules are being broken
أدنى فكرة عن القوانين التي تم تجاوزها
thousands of times every year?
آلاف المرات سنويًا؟
CA: Ed, one response to this whole debate is this:
كريس: إد إعطني إجابة واحدة للرد على الجدل حول:
Why should we care about
بصدق لماذا علينا أن نهتم
all this surveillance, honestly?
بهذه الرقابة؟
I mean, look, if you've done nothing wrong,
أقصد إذا لم تفعل شيئًا خاطئًا
you've got nothing to worry about.
ليس هنالك مايجب أن تقلق منه.
What's wrong with that point of view?
ما الخطأ في وجهة النظر هذه؟
ES: Well, so the first thing is,
إد: حسنًا أول شيء هو
you're giving up your rights.
أنك تتنازل عن حقوقك.
You're saying hey, you know,
أنت تخبرهم
I don't think I'm going to need them,
أنك لست بحاجة إليها.
so I'm just going to trust that, you know,
إذن أنا واثق
let's get rid of them, it doesn't really matter,
أنه سيتم التخلص منها لأنها غير مهمة
these guys are going to do the right thing.
هؤلاء الأشخاص سيقومون بالشيء الصحيح
Your rights matter
حقوقك مهمة
because you never know when you're going to need them.
لأنك لا تعرف متى ستحتاجهم.
Beyond that, it's a part of our cultural identity,
أبعد من ذلك هي جزء من هويتنا الثقافية
not just in America,
ليس فقط في أمريكا
but in Western societies
لكن في المجتمعات الغربية
and in democratic societies around the world.
وفي المجتمعات الديموقراطية حول العالم.
People should be able to pick up the phone
على الأشخاص أن يستطيعوا حمل سماعة الهاتف
and to call their family,
والإتصال بعائلتهم
people should be able to send a text message
على الأشخاص أن يستطيعوا إرسال رسائل نصية
to their loved ones,
لأحبائهم
people should be able to buy a book online,
على الأشخاص أن يستطيعوا شراء كتاب من على الإنترنت
they should be able to travel by train,
يجب أن يستطيعوا السفر بالقطار
they should be able to buy an airline ticket
و أن يشتروا تذاكر طائرة
without wondering about how these events
من دون أن يتسألوا كيف بإمكان هذه الحوادث أن
are going to look to an agent of the government,
تبدو لأي عميل في الحكومة
possibly not even your government
محتمل ليس عميلاً في حكومتك
years in the future,
خلال سنوات من الآن
how they're going to be misinterpreted
كيف سيتم إساءت تفسيرها
and what they're going to think your intentions were.
و كيف سيفكرون في نواياك وقتها؟
We have a right to privacy.
نحن لدينا حق للخصوصية.
We require warrants to be based on probable cause
نحن نطالب بتسويات تقوم على سبب محتمل
or some kind of individualized suspicion
أو أي نوع من الإشتباه الفردي
because we recognize that trusting anybody,
لأننا ندرك أن نوكل لأي شخص
any government authority,
أو أي سلطة حكومية
with the entirety of human communications
أمر مجمل الإتصالات الإنسانية
in secret and without oversight
في سرية ومن دون رقابة
is simply too great a temptation to be ignored.
ببساطة هي فتنة عظيمة لايمكن تجاهلها.
CA: Some people are furious at what you've done.
كريس: بعض الناس غاضبين بشدة لأجل مافعلته.
I heard a quote recently from Dick Cheney
سمعت مؤخرًا إقتباسًا من ديك تشيني
who said that Julian Assange was a flea bite,
والذي قال جوليان اسانج كانت لدغة البرغوثة
Edward Snowden is the lion that bit the head off the dog.
لكن إدورد سنودن هو الأسد الذي عض رأس الكلب
He thinks you've committed
هو يعتقد أنك إرتكبت
one of the worst acts of betrayal
أحد أسوأ الخيانات
in American history.
في التاريخ الأمريكي
What would you say to people who think that?
ماذا تقول للأشخاص الذين يعتقدون ذلك؟
ES: Dick Cheney's really something else.
إد: ديك شيني شيء آخر.
(Laughter) (Applause)
(ضحك)(تصفيق)
Thank you. (Laughter)
شكرًا. (ضحك)
I think it's amazing, because at the time
اعتقد أنه مدهش لأنه في الوقت
Julian Assange was doing some of his greatest work,
الذي كان يقوم فيه جوليان آسانج بأعظم أعماله
Dick Cheney was saying
كان يقول ديك تشينى
he was going to end governments worldwide,
أنه سينهي الحكومات على مستوى العالم
the skies were going to ignite
وأن السموات ستشتعل
and the seas were going to boil off,
وأن البحار ستغلي
and now he's saying it's a flea bite.
والآن يتحدث عن لدغة برغوث.
So we should be suspicious about the same sort of
إذن علينا أن نكون حذرين عن
overblown claims of damage to national security
قضايا الأمن القومي التي يتم تضخيمها
from these kind of officials.
من قبل هذا النوع من المسؤولين؟
But let's assume that these people really believe this.
لكن دعونا نفترض أن هؤلاء الأشخاص يؤمنون بذلك حقًا
I would argue that they have kind of
بإمكاني أن أناقش أن لديهم نوع
a narrow conception of national security.
من الفهم الضيق للأمن القومي.
The prerogatives of people like Dick Cheney
سلطات الأشخاص مثل ديك تشيني
do not keep the nation safe.
لا تحافظ على أمننا القومي.
The public interest is not always the same
المصلحة العامة لا تتفق
as the national interest.
دائمًا مع المصلحة الوطنية.
Going to war with people who are not our enemy
المضي في حرب مع أشخاص ليسوا أعداء لنا
in places that are not a threat
في أماكن لاتمثل تهديد
doesn't make us safe,
لا تجعلنا اكثر أمنًا
and that applies whether it's in Iraq
وهذا ينطبق سواءًا على العراق
or on the Internet.
او في الإنترنت.
The Internet is not the enemy.
الإنترنت ليس العدو.
Our economy is not the enemy.
إقتصادنا ليس العدو.
American businesses, Chinese businesses,
التجارة الأمريكية والتجارة الصينية
and any other company out there
وأي شركة هنالك
is a part of our society.
هي جزء من مجتمعنا.
It's a part of our interconnected world.
هي جزء من عالمنا المتواصل.
There are ties of fraternity that bond us together,
هنالك روابط أخوية تجمعنا.
and if we destroy these bonds
وإذا دمرنا هذه الروابط
by undermining the standards, the security,
بتقويض القيم و الأمن
the manner of behavior,
والسلوك
that nations and citizens all around the world
الذي يتوقع منا كل المواطنين والأمم حول العالم
expect us to abide by.
أن نلتزم به.
CA: But it's alleged that you've stolen
كريس: لكن تم زعم أنك سرقت
1.7 million documents.
1.7 مليون مستند
It seems only a few hundred of them
لكن يبدو أن بعض المئات منها
have been shared with journalists so far.
تم مشاركتها مع الصحفيين
Are there more revelations to come?
هل نتوقع الكشف عن أشياء أخرى؟
ES: There are absolutely more revelations to come.
إد: بالتأكيد هنالك العديد من التصريحات لتلحق
I don't think there's any question
لا أعتقد أن هنالك أي سؤال
that some of the most important reporting
أن بعض أهم التقارير
to be done is yet to come.
لم تصدر بعد.
CA: Come here, because I want to ask you
كريس: تعال هنا لأني أريد أن أسألك
about this particular revelation.
عن تصريح محدد.
Come and take a look at this.
تعال وخذ نظرة على هذا.
I mean, this is a story which I think for a lot of the techies in this room
أقصد أن هذه قصة للعديد من التقنين في هذه الغرفة
is the single most shocking thing
تطرح أكثر موضوع صدمهم
that they have heard in the last few months.
خلال الأشهر القليلة الماضية.
It's about a program called "Bullrun."
إنه عن برنامج يسمى "بول ران"
Can you explain what that is?
هل لك أن تشرحه لنا؟
ES: So Bullrun, and this is again
إد: حسنًا بول ران مرة اخرى
where we've got to thank the NSA for their candor,
علينا أن نشكر ال NSA لصراحتها
this is a program named after a Civil War battle.
هذا برنامج تم تسميته بعد أحد معارك الحرب الأهلية
The British counterpart is called Edgehill,
نظير الإسم البريطاني هو " إدجهيل"
which is a U.K. civil war battle.
والتي هي أحد المعارك في الحرب الأهلية البريطانية.
And the reason that I believe they're named this way
والسبب الذي أعتقد لأجله أنه تمت تسميتهم كذلك
is because they target our own infrastructure.
لأنها تستهدف بنياتنا التحتية
They're programs through which the NSA
هي برامج من خلالها الNSA
intentionally misleads corporate partners.
تقصد تضليل الشركات المشاركة.
They tell corporate partners that these
هم يخبرونهم أن هذه
are safe standards.
معايير سليمة
They say hey, we need to work with you
يقولون نريد أن نعمل معكم
to secure your systems,
كي نؤمن أنظمتكم
but in reality, they're giving bad advice
لكن الحقيقة أنهم يعطون نصيحة
to these companies that makes them
لهذه الشركات والتي
degrade the security of their services.
توهن من أمن خدماتهم.
They're building in backdoors that not only
هم يبنون خلف الأبواب ليس فقط مابإمكان
the NSA can exploit,
ال NSA إستغلاله
but anyone else who has time and money
لكن أي شخص أخر لديه الوقت والمال
to research and find it
بإمكانه أن يبحث عنه ويجده
can then use to let themselves in
ثم يستخدمه للدخول
to the world's communications.
إلى عالم الإتصالات
And this is really dangerous,
وهذا خطر للغاية
because if we lose a single standard,
لأننا إذا خسرنا معيار واحد
if we lose the trust of something like SSL,
إذا خسرنا الثقة في الSSL
which was specifically targeted
والذي كان مستهدف تحديدًأ
by the Bullrun program,
من قبل برنامج ال" بول ران"
we will live a less safe world overall.
سنعيش في عالم أقل أمنًا.
We won't be able to access our banks
لن نستطيع الدخول إلى بنوكنا
and we won't be able to access commerce
ولن نستطيع الدخول إلى التجارة
without worrying about people monitoring those communications
من غير أن نقلق من أن هؤلاء الأشخاص يراقبون إتصالاتنا
or subverting them for their own ends.
أو يخربونها لأجل مصلحتهم
CA: And do those same decisions also potentially
كريس: وهل هذه القرارات تحتمل
open America up to cyberattacks
تعريض أمريكا للهجمات السيبرانية
from other sources?
من مصادر أخرى
ES: Absolutely.
إد: بكل تأكيد
One of the problems,
أحد المشاكل
one of the dangerous legacies
و أخطر الموروثات
that we've seen in the post-9/11 era,
التي رأينها بعد أحداث 9/11
is that the NSA has traditionally worn two hats.
هي أن ال NSA لبست تقليديًا قبعتان.
They've been in charge of offensive operations,
صاروا يتحكمون بالعمليات الهجومية
that is hacking,
والتي هي القرصنة,
but they've also been in charge of defensive operations,
لكن أيضًا صاروا يتحكمون بالعمليات الدفاعية
and traditionally they've always prioritized
و تقليديًا هم دائمًا أعطوا الأولوية
defense over offense
للدفاع مقابل الهجوم
based on the principle
إستنادًا إلى قانون
that American secrets are simply worth more.
أن الأسرار الأمريكية أكثر أهمية
If we hack a Chinese business
إذا إخترقنا التجارة الصينية
and steal their secrets,
وسرقنا أسرارهم
if we hack a government office in Berlin
إذا هاجمنا مكاتب الحكومة في برلين
that has less value to the American people
لذلك أهمية اقل للأمريكان
than making sure that the Chinese
من التأكد من أن الصينين
can't get access to our secrets.
لن يستطيعوا النفاذ إلى أسرارنا.
So by reducing the security of our communications,
إذن من خلال تقليل أمن إتصالاتنا
they're not only putting the world at risk,
هم لايضعون العالم فقط في خطر
they're putting America at risk in a fundamental way,
هم يضعون أمريكا في خطر بطريقة أساسية
because intellectual property is the basis,
لأن الأولويات الفكرية هي أساسيات
the foundation of our economy,
و دعامات إقتصادنا
and if we put that at risk through weak security,
وإذا عرضنا ذلك للخطر عن طريق إضعاف أمننا
we're going to be paying for it for years.
سندفع الثمن لسنين
CA: But they've made a calculation
كريس: لكنهم قاموا بحسابات
that it was worth doing this
أثبتت أهمية القيام بذلك
as part of America's defense against terrorism.
كجزء من دفاع أمريكا ضد الإرهاب.
Surely that makes it a price worth paying.
بالتأكيد هذا يجعله ثمن جيد.
ES: Well, when you look at the results
إد: حسنًا عندما تنظر إلى نتائج هذه البرامج
of these programs in stopping terrorism,
في إيقاف الإرهاب
you will see that that's unfounded,
سترى أنه لا أساس لها من الصحة
and you don't have to take my word for it,
وليس عليك أن تأخذ بكلامي
because we've had the first open court,
لأننا عقدنا أول محكمة مفتوحة
the first federal court that's reviewed this,
فيدرالية راجعت هذا الموضوع
outside the secrecy arrangement,
خارج الإجراء السري
called these programs Orwellian
سمت هذه البرامج غريبة
and likely unconstitutional.
ولا علاقة لها بالدستور.
Congress, who has access
الكونغرس والذي كان لديه حرية الوصول
to be briefed on these things,
و الإطلاع على هذه الأشياء
and now has the desire to be,
الآن لديه الرغبة
has produced bills to reform it,
لإصدار مذكرات لإصلاحها
and two independent White House panels
كما أن ندوتان مستقلتان في البيت الأبيض
who reviewed all of the classified evidence
راجعت كل هذه الأدلة المصنفة
said these programs have never stopped
وقالت أن هذه البرامج لم توقف قط
a single terrorist attack
أية هجمة إرهابية
that was imminent in the United States.
أوشكت على الحدوث في الولايات المتحدة.
So is it really terrorism that we're stopping?
إذن ما نحاول إيقافه هل هو حقيقة الإرهاب؟
Do these programs have any value at all?
هل لهذه البرامج أية قيمة على الإطلاق؟
I say no, and all three branches
أجيب لا وكل الفروع الثلاثة
of the American government say no as well.
للحكومة الأمريكية تقول أيضًا لا.
CA: I mean, do you think there's a deeper motivation
كريس: أقصد هل تعتقد أن هنالك حافز أعمق
for them than the war against terrorism?
من الحرب ضد الإرهاب؟
ES: I'm sorry, I couldn't hear you, say again?
إد: عذراً لم أقدر على سماعك, اعد مرة أخرى؟
CA: Sorry. Do you think there's a deeper motivation
كريس: عذرًا, هل تعتقد أن هنالك حافز أعمق
for them other than the war against terrorism?
بالنسبة لهم اكثر من الحرب ضد الإرهاب؟
ES: Yeah. The bottom line is that terrorism
إد: نعم الخلاصة هي أن الحرب على الإرهاب
has always been what we in the intelligence world
دائمًا كانت مانسميه في عالم الإستخبارات
would call a cover for action.
بغطاء العملية.
Terrorism is something that provokes
الإرهاب هو شيء يثير
an emotional response that allows people
تجاوب عاطفي يسمح للناس
to rationalize authorizing powers and programs
بتسويغ السماح بسلطات وبرامج
that they wouldn't give otherwise.
لن يسمحوا بها في اية حالة أخرى.
The Bullrun and Edgehill-type programs,
ال" بول ران" و ال" إدهيج" هي من نوع البرامج
the NSA asked for these authorities
التي طالبت ال NSA بإجازتها
back in the 1990s.
في التسعينات
They asked the FBI to go to Congress and make the case.
هم طلبوا من ال FBI أن يرفعوا القضية إلى الكونغرس
The FBI went to Congress and did make the case.
رفعت الFBI القضية
But Congress and the American people said no.
لكن الكونغرس و الشعب الأمريكي رفض.
They said, it's not worth the risk to our economy.
هي ليست ذات قيمة لتهديد إقتصادنا
They said it's worth too much damage
كما قالوا أنها ستولد ضرر
to our society to justify the gains.
أكبر لمجتمعنا والذي لايمكنه تبرير المنافع.
But what we saw is, in the post-9/11 era,
ولكن مارأيناه في عهد مابعد 9/11
they used secrecy and they used the justification of terrorism
أنهم أستخدموا السرية ومبررات الإرهاب
to start these programs in secret
ليبدأوا بهذه البرامج سرًا
without asking Congress,
من غير سؤال الكونغرس
without asking the American people,
أو الشعب الأمريكي
and it's that kind of government behind closed doors
أيضًا هذا هو نوع الحكومة التي تعمل خلف الأدوار المغلقة
that we need to guard ourselves against,
والتي نحتاج لأن نحمي أنفسنا ضدها
because it makes us less safe,
لأنها تجعلنا أقل أمنًا
and it offers no value.
كما لا توفر أية قيمة.
CA: Okay, come with me here for a sec,
كريس: حسنًا تعال معي هاهنا لثانية
because I've got a more personal question for you.
لأنني سأطرح عليك سؤالاً شخصيًا.
Speaking of terror,
عندما نتحدث عن الإرهاب
most people would find the situation you're in right now
معظم الناس يجدون الوضع الذي أنت فيه الآن
in Russia pretty terrifying.
في روسيا مخيف جدًا.
You obviously heard what happened,
أنت محتمل سمعت عما حدث
what the treatment that Bradley Manning got,
المعاملة التي تلقاها برادلي مانينغ
Chelsea Manning as now is,
تشيلسا مانينغ حاليًا
and there was a story in Buzzfeed saying that
وكانت هنالك قصة في بازفيد تقول أن
there are people in the intelligence community
هنالك أشخاص في جهاز الإستخبارات
who want you dead.
يريدونك ميتًا.
How are you coping with this?
كيف تتأقلم مع هذا الوضع؟
How are you coping with the fear?
كيف تتأقلم مع الخوف؟
ES: It's no mystery
إد: ليس لغزًا
that there are governments out there that want to see me dead.
أن هنالك بعض الحكومات تريدني ميتًا
I've made clear again and again and again
وضحت مرارًا وتكرارًا
that I go to sleep every morning
أنني أنام كل صباح
thinking about what I can do for the American people.
وأفكر ماذا يمكن أن أفعل للشعب الأمريكي.
I don't want to harm my government.
أنا لأريد أن اؤذي حكومتي.
I want to help my government,
أريد أن اساعدها
but the fact that they are willing to
لكن حقيقة أنهم يرغبون
completely ignore due process,
في تجاهل الإجراءات القانونية المطلوبة
they're willing to declare guilt
هم أيضًا يرغبون في إتهامي بالذنب
without ever seeing a trial,
من دون مشاهدة أية محاكمة
these are things that we need to work against
هذه هي الأشياء التي نحتاج أن نعمل ضدها
as a society, and say hey, this is not appropriate.
كمجتمع علينا أن نعلن أنها غير ملائمة.
We shouldn't be threatening dissidents.
لا يجب علينا تهديد المارقين
We shouldn't be criminalizing journalism.
و لاتجريم الصحفين
And whatever part I can do to see that end,
و أي شي بإمكاني القيام به لإنهاء ذلك
I'm happy to do despite the risks.
أنا سعيد بالقيام به رغم الخطر.
CA: So I'd actually like to get some feedback
كريس: أريد أن أخذ رأي
from the audience here,
بعض الحضور هنا
because I know there's widely differing reactions
لأنني أعرف أن هنالك ردود فعل مختلفة
to Edward Snowden.
لإدوارد سنودن
Suppose you had the following two choices, right?
إفترض أن لديك هذين الخيارين حاليًا؟
You could view what he did
بإمكانك أن ترى مافعله
as fundamentally a reckless act
كعمل متهور في الأساس
that has endangered America
وضع أمريكا في خطر
or you could view it as fundamentally a heroic act
أم تراهٌ كعمل ذو أساس بطولي
that will work towards America and the world's
بإمكانه أن يخدم أمريكا والعالم
long-term good?
على المدى الطويل؟
Those are the two choices I'll give you.
هذان همها الخياران اللذان ساعطيك.
I'm curious to see who's willing to vote with
أنا متحرق لأرى من سيصوت
the first of those,
للخيار الأول
that this was a reckless act?
أن هذا كان عملاً مٌتهورًا؟
There are some hands going up.
هنالك بعض الأيادي مرفوعة؟
Some hands going up.
بعض الأيادي إرتفعت.
It's hard to put your hand up
يصعب أن ترفع يدك
when the man is standing right here,
عندما يقف الشخص أمامك هاهنا
but I see them.
لكني أرى تلك الأيادي.
ES: I can see you. (Laughter)
إد: بإمكاني أن أراك (ضحك)
CA: And who goes with the second choice,
كريس: ومن يتفق مع الخيار الثاني
the fundamentally heroic act?
عمل ذو أساس بطولي؟
(Applause) (Cheers)
(تصفيق)(تشجيع)
And I think it's true to say that there are a lot of people
أيضًا من الصحيح أن العديد لم
who didn't show a hand and I think
يرفعوا أيديهم
are still thinking this through,
مازالوا يفكرون في هذا الأمر
because it seems to me that the debate around you
لأنه يبدو لي أن النقاش حولك
doesn't split along traditional political lines.
لا يتحيز للخطوط السياسية المتعارف عليها.
It's not left or right, it's not really about
هو ليس يساري أو يميني, هو ليس عن
pro-government, libertarian, or not just that.
أنصار الحكومة الأحرار أو أن جزء منه
Part of it is almost a generational issue.
قضية عامة فقط.
You're part of a generation that grew up
أنت جزء من جيل تربى
with the Internet, and it seems as if
على الإنترنت وكما يبدو
you become offended at almost a visceral level
أنك أصبحت تستاء حتى الأعماق
when you see something done
إذا رأيت شيئًا يتم القيام به
that you think will harm the Internet.
وتعتقد أنه سيؤذي الإنترنت.
Is there some truth to that?
هل هنالك شيء من الحقيقة في هذا؟
ES: It is. I think it's very true.
إد: هو كذلك. أعتقد أنه صحيح.
This is not a left or right issue.
هذا ليس موضوعًا لليسار أو اليمين.
Our basic freedoms, and when I say our,
حرياتنا الأساسية وعندما أقول ذلك
I don't just mean Americans,
لست أقصد الأمريكان
I mean people around the world,
أعني كل الناس حول العالم
it's not a partisan issue.
هو ليس أمرًا حزبيًا.
These are things that all people believe,
هذه أشياء يؤمن بها جميع الناس
and it's up to all of us to protect them,
و مسؤليتنا جميعًا أن نحميها
and to people who have seen and enjoyed
و مسؤلية الأشخاص الذين أستمتعوا
a free and open Internet,
بإنترنت مفتوح و مجاني
it's up to us to preserve that liberty
إنها مسؤليتنا لنحافظ على هذه الحرية
for the next generation to enjoy,
للجيل القادم حتى يستمتع بها
and if we don't change things,
وإذا لم نغير الأشياء
if we don't stand up to make the changes
إذا لم نقف لإحداث التغيرات
we need to do to keep the Internet safe,
التي نحتاجها للحفاظ على إنترنت آمن
not just for us but for everyone,
ليس فقط لأجلنا لكن للجميع
we're going to lose that,
سنخسر ذلك
and that would be a tremendous loss,
وستكون خسارة كبيرة
not just for us, but for the world.
ليس فقط لنا لكن للعالم.
CA: Well, I have heard similar language recently
كريس: حسنًا سمعت لغة مشابهة
from the founder of the world wide web,
من مؤسس الشبكة العنكبوتية العالمية
who I actually think is with us, Sir Tim Berners-Lee.
والذي أعتقد أنه موجود معنا سير تيم بِرنارز لي
Tim, actually, would you like to come up and say,
تيم, في الواقع هل تود أن تأتي وتخبرنا
do we have a microphone for Tim?
هل لدينا مايكرفون لتيم؟
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Tim, good to see you. Come up there.
تيم من الجيد أن أراك تأتي هنا
Which camp are you in, by the way,
بالمناسبة أية جهة تنتمي إليها
traitor, hero? I have a theory on this, but --
خائن, بطل؟ لدي نظرية في هذا لكن
Tim Berners-Lee: I've given much longer
تيم: أعطيت بعض الأجوبة المطولة لذلك
answers to that question, but hero,
لكن بطل
if I have to make the choice between the two.
إذا كان علي أن أختار بين الإثنين.
CA: And Ed, I think you've read
كريس: أعتقد أنك قرأت
the proposal that Sir Tim has talked about
المقترح الذي تحدث عنه سير تيم
about a new Magna Carta to take back the Internet.
عن ماغنا كارتا جديدة لإسترجاع الإنترنت
Is that something that makes sense?
هل هذا شيء منطقي؟
ES: Absolutely. I mean, my generation, I grew up
إد: بالتأكيد أعني جيلي لم أكبر
not just thinking about the Internet,
فقط وأنا أفكر في الإنترنت
but I grew up in the Internet,
لكني كبرت داخل الإنترنت
and although I never expected to have the chance
وبالرغم من أنني لم أتوقع أن أحصل على الفرصة
to defend it in such a direct and practical manner
للدفاع عنه بطريقة مباشرة و عملية
and to embody it in this unusual,
و كي أجسده بطريقة غير عادية
almost avatar manner,
تقريبًا طريقة رمزية
I think there's something poetic about the fact that
أعتقد أن هنالك طريقة شاعرية عن هذه الحقيقة
one of the sons of the Internet
أحد أبناء الإنترنت
has actually become close to the Internet
حقيقة أصبح قريبًا من الإنترنت
as a result of their political expression.
كنتيجة للتعبير عن إتجاهه السياسي.
And I believe that a Magna Carta for the Internet
و أعتقد أن ماغنا كارتا للإنترنت
is exactly what we need.
هي تمامًا ما نحتاج
We need to encode our values
نحن نحتاج لترميز قيمنا
not just in writing but in the structure of the Internet,
ليس فقط من خلال الكتابة لكن في هيكل الإنترنت
and it's something that I hope,
وهو شيء آمل
I invite everyone in the audience,
أن أدعو إليه كل شخص من الحضور
not just here in Vancouver but around the world,
ليس فقط هنا في فانكوفر لكن حول العالم
to join and participate in.
حتى ينضموا و يشاركوا.
CA: Do you have a question for Ed?
كريس: هل لديك سؤال لإد؟
TBL: Well, two questions,
تيم: حسنًا سؤالان
a general question —
سؤال عام
CA: Ed, can you still hear us?
كريس: إد هل مازلت تسمعنا؟
ES: Yes, I can hear you. CA: Oh, he's back.
إد: نعم بإمكاني أن أسمعك كريس: اه لقد رجع.
TBL: The wiretap on your line
تيم: خط التنصت عندك
got a little interfered with for a moment.
تم إعتراضه للحظة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
ES: It's a little bit of an NSA problem.
إد: هي مشكلة صغيرة من الNSA
TBL: So, from the 25 years,
تيم: إذن من خلال ال25 سنة الماضية
stepping back and thinking,
بإمكاني أن أرجع وأفكر
what would you think would be
ماذا يمكن برأيكم أن يكون
the best that we could achieve
أفضل شيء يمكننا إنجازه
from all the discussions that we have
من كل هذه المناقشات
about the web we want?
عن الشبكة التي نريدها؟
ES: When we think about
إد: عندما نفكر
in terms of how far we can go,
كم بإمكاننا أن ننجز
I think that's a question that's really only limited
أعتقد أنه سؤال مقيد
by what we're willing to put into it.
برغبتنا لخدمة القضية.
I think the Internet that we've enjoyed in the past
أعتقد أن الإنترنت الذي إستمتعنا به في الماضي
has been exactly what we as not just a nation
اصبح تمامًا ما إحتجناه ليس فقط كأمة
but as a people around the world need,
لكن مايحتاجه كل الناس حول العالم
and by cooperating, by engaging not just
وبالتعاون ليس فقط بإشراك
the technical parts of society,
الجزء التقني من المجتمع
but as you said, the users,
لكن كما قلت المستخدمين
the people around the world who contribute
الأشخاص حول العام الذين يساهمون
through the Internet, through social media,
عبر الإنترنت والأوساط الإجتماعية
who just check the weather,
الذين يتحرون فقط الطقس
who rely on it every day as a part of their life,
والذين يعتمدون عليه يوميًا كجزء من حياتهم
to champion that.
كي يدافعوا عنه.
We'll get not just the Internet we've had,
نحن لن نحصل فقط على الإنترنت الذي كان لدينا
but a better Internet, a better now,
لكن إنترنت أفضل
something that we can use to build a future
شيء يمكننا أن نستخدمة كي نبني مستقبل
that'll be better not just than what we hoped for
سيصبح أفضل ليس فقط مما آملنا
but anything that we could have imagined.
لكن من أي شي تخيلناه.
CA: It's 30 years ago that TED was founded, 1984.
كريس: ثلاثون عامًا عندما تأسست TED
A lot of the conversation since then has been
الكثير من المحادثات منذ ذلك الوقت
along the lines that
كانت حول النصوص
actually George Orwell got it wrong.
التي أخطأ فيها جورج أوريل.
It's not Big Brother watching us.
ليس الأخ الأكبر هو الذي يراقبنا.
We, through the power of the web,
نحن من خلال سلطة الشبكة
and transparency, are now watching Big Brother.
و الشفافية نراقب الأخ الأكبر.
Your revelations kind of drove a stake
تصريحاتك نوع الما حطمت
through the heart of that rather optimistic view,
وجهات النظر المتفائلة
but you still believe there's a way of doing something
لكنك مازلت تؤمن أن هنالك طريقة للقيام
about that.
بشيء حياله.
And you do too.
وأنت تفعل ذلك.
ES: Right, so there is an argument to be made
إد: صحيح هنالك حجة لابد أن تقام
that the powers of Big Brother have increased enormously.
هي أن سلطات الأخ الأكبر قد إزدادت بشكل هائل.
There was a recent legal article at Yale
هنالك مقال حديث في جامعة يال
that established something called the Bankston-Soltani Principle,
والذي أسس شيئًا يسمى قاعدة بانكستون سولتاني
which is that our expectation of privacy is violated
والتي تتطرق لأن الخصوصية التي توقعناها تم التعدي عليها
when the capabilities of government surveillance
عندما اصبحت قدرات الرقابة الحكومية
have become cheaper by an order of magnitude,
متدنية في قيمتها الأسية.
and each time that occurs, we need to revisit
وفي كل مرة يحدث ذلك نحتاج لأن نراجع
and rebalance our privacy rights.
ونوازن حقوقنا في الخصوصية
Now, that hasn't happened since
الآن لم يحدث هذا منذ
the government's surveillance powers
أن إزدادت سلطات الحكومة
have increased by several orders of magnitude,
الرقابية بمقدار أسي
and that's why we're in the problem that we're in today,
ولأجل ذلك نحن نواجه اليوم هذه المشكلة
but there is still hope,
لكن مازال هنالك أمل,
because the power of individuals
لأن قوة الأشخاص
have also been increased by technology.
قد إزدادت أيضًا عن طريق التكنولوجيا
I am living proof
وأنا أكبر مثال على
that an individual can go head to head
أن بإمكان شخص أن يمضي رأسًا برأس
against the most powerful adversaries
متحديًا أكثر الخصوم قوة
and the most powerful intelligence agencies
أكثر وكالات الإستخبارات قوة
around the world and win,
حول العالم و ينجح,
and I think that's something
و أفكر أن هذا شيء
that we need to take hope from,
علينا أن نتفائل به
and we need to build on
و نبني عليه
to make it accessible not just to technical experts
لجعله متاح ليس فقط للخبراء التقنين
but to ordinary citizens around the world.
لكن للمواطنين العادين حول العالم
Journalism is not a crime,
الصحافة ليست جريمة
communication is not a crime,
الإتصال ليس جريمة
and we should not be monitored in our everyday activities.
ونحن لا يجب أن نراقب في نشاطاتنا اليومية.
CA: I'm not quite sure how you shake the hand of a bot,
كريس: أنا لست متأكد كيف بإمكانك أن تصافح يد الروبوت
but I imagine it's, this is the hand right here. TBL: That'll come very soon.
لكن تخيل أن هذه اليد هاهنا. تيم: سف يتم إختراعها قريبًا.
ES: Nice to meet you,
إد: سعيد بلقائك
and I hope my beam looks as nice
و أتمنى أن تبدو صورتي جيدة
as my view of you guys does.
كما الصورة التي أراكم بها.
CA: Thank you, Tim.
كرس: شكرًا تيم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
I mean, The New York Times recently called for an amnesty for you.
أقصد أن جريدة النيويورك تايمز طالبت بإصدار صفح عام عنك.
Would you welcome the chance to come back to America?
هل ترحب بفرصة القدوم إلى أمريكا مرة أخرى؟
ES: Absolutely. There's really no question,
إد: بالتأكيد حقيقة لايوجد سؤال
the principles that have been the foundation
المبادىء التي كونت أساس
of this project
هذا المشروع
have been the public interest
كانت للمصلحة العامة
and the principles that underly
وللمبادىء التي تقوم
the journalistic establishment in the United States
عليها الصحافة في الولايات المتحدة
and around the world,
و حول العالم
and I think if the press is now saying,
وأعتقد إذا اخبر الإعلام أنهم
we support this,
يدعمون ذلك
this is something that needed to happen,
على هذا الشيء أن يحدث
that's a powerful argument, but it's not the final argument,
هذه حجة قوية لكنها ليست الحجة الأخيرة
and I think that's something that public should decide.
و أعتقد أن هذا شيء على العامة ان يقرروه
But at the same time,
لكن في نفس الوقت
the government has hinted that they want
الحكومة لمحت
some kind of deal,
أنها تريد نوع من صفقة
that they want me to compromise
هم يريدونني أن أفضح
the journalists with which I've been working,
الصحافين الذين أتعامل معهم
to come back,
حتى أعود,
and I want to make it very clear
و أريد أن أوضح
that I did not do this to be safe.
أنني لم أفعل ذلك كي أكون آمن
I did this to do what was right,
فعلت ذلك كي أقوم بالصواب
and I'm not going to stop my work
ولن أوقف عملي لخدمة
in the public interest
المصلحة العامة
just to benefit myself.
فقط كي أخدم نفسي.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
CA: In the meantime,
كريس: في الوقت المناسب
courtesy of the Internet and this technology,
كمجاملة للإنترنت وهذه التكنولوجيا
you're here, back in North America,
عدت هنا إلى شمال أمريكا
not quite the U.S., Canada, in this form.
ليس الولايات المتحدة لكن كندا بهذه الصورة.
I'm curious, how does that feel?
أنا متحمس لكي أعرف كيف تشعر؟
ES: Canada is different than what I expected.
إد: كندا مختلفة عما توقعته.
It's a lot warmer.
هي أكثر دفئ.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
CA: At TED, the mission is "ideas worth spreading."
كريس: هاهنا في TED مهمتنا نشر الأفكار القيمة
If you could encapsulate it in a single idea,
هل بإمكانك إختصار هذه المحادثة في فكرة واحدة
what is your idea worth spreading
ماهي فكرتك التي تستحق النشر
right now at this moment?
الآن في هذه اللحظة؟
ES: I would say the last year has been a reminder
إد: بمقدوري أن أقول أن السنة الماضية ذكرتنا
that democracy may die behind closed doors,
أن الديمقراطية بإمكانها أن تموت خلف الأبواب المغلقة
but we as individuals are born
لكننا كأشخاص ولدنا
behind those same closed doors,
خلف هذه الأبواب المغلقة
and we don't have to give up
و ليس علينا أن نعطي
our privacy to have good government.
خصوصيتنا كي نحصل على حكومة جيدة.
We don't have to give up our liberty
ليس علينا التخلي عن حريتنا
to have security.
للحصول على الأمن
And I think by working together
وأعتقد من خلال العمل معًا
we can have both open government
يمكننا أن نحصل على حكومة مفتوحة
and private lives,
وحياة خاصة
and I look forward to working with everyone
و أتوق للعمل مع كل شخص
around the world to see that happen.
حول العالم كي أرى ذلك يحدث.
Thank you very much.
شكرًا جزيلاً.
CA: Ed, thank you.
كريس: إد شكرًا لك.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)